All right, we're going to start. Today's דף *daf*, I didn't mean
to be... י"ד *Yud-Daled*, we start two lines from the bottom, and
the משנה Mishna, *Mishnah* on the bottom of י"ג עמוד ב' *Yud-Gimmel
Amud-Beis*.
So we had talked about, we're talking about numbers of חטאת chatas.
*chatos* you can bring when you eat less than a כזית kezayit
*kezayis* or a full כזית kezayit. *kezayis* over a long period of
time. If you eat multiple כזיתים kezayitim. *kezaysin* in one, it translates
into multiple חטאות chata'ot, *chatosos* if it's different types of things or
if you remember in between, and when it's only one חטאת *chatos*.
And now we go on in that vein.
So the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* on the bottom of י"ג עמוד ב'
*Yud-Gimmel Amud-Beis*: יש אוכל אכילה אחת וחייב עליה ארבע חטאות chataos. *Yesh
ochel achilah achas vechayav aleha arba chatos*. So as opposed to one
type of like eating multiple כזיתים kezayitim. *kezaysin*, two כזיתים kezayitim. *kezaysin*
of חלב Chelev. *cheilev*, is it two חטאות *chatosos* or one? One
כזית kezayit *kezayis* of חלב Chelev, *cheilev*, one כזית kezayit *kezayis* of
דם dam *dam*. Here we have like the reverse. One כזית kezayit,
*kezayis* and you get multiple חטאת *chatos*. And now the משניות Mishnayot
*Mishnayos* are going to have fun essentially by basically saying like, you
know, how many sin offerings can you bring by doing one sin,
by doing one act? So you have the parallel discussion in מכות
*Makkos* where it says how many times, how many different lashes can
you get for doing one type of an act? Okay, so here
it's parallel, like כריתות kareisos *krisos* in certain ways parallels מכות *Makkos*.
מכות *Makkos* is about what you get lashes for and how many
lashes you can bring, and when you get different numbers, different number,
you know, when, you know, if you did one, if you ate
a lot of forbidden things, is it one set of lashes or
multiple? And this is a similar discussion about sin offerings when it's
בשוגג *beshogeg*. So how can you, there's ways you can eat one
thing and bring four sin offerings, okay, because there's four different sins
wrapped up in this one thing that you're eating. Let's take a
look. ואשם אחד *Ve'asham echad*. Not only four sin offerings, one אשם
*asham*. טמא Tamei. שאכל חלב chelev, *Tamei she'achal cheilev*, you're a טמא
Tamei? *tamei* person and you ate fat, so fat is one sin
offering, טמא Tamei, *tamei* is not yet a problem. And this is
all בשוגג *beshogeg*, unintentionally. והוא נותר notar. *Vehu nosar*, and it is
leftover sacrifices, so נותר notar, *nosar* is כרת *kares*, so that's another
sin offering. מן המוקדשין *Min hamukdashin*, it is sanctified, obviously it's נותר
notar *nosar*, it's a קרבן korban *korban*, and you're טמא Tamei; *tamei*.
So because you're טמא tamei *tamei*, a טמא tamei, *tamei* that ate
from קדשים Kodshim *kodshim* is another קרבן korban, *korban*, it's עולה ויורד
*oleh veyored*, but that's three. ביום הכיפורים *Beyom hakippurim*, on יום כיפור
Yom Kippur. *Yom Kippur*, so that is number four, right? You get
כרת *kares* for יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*, this is בשוגג
*beshogeg*. Now where is the אשם *asham*? The אשם *asham* is, is
that since it is a, that it's מעילה Me'ilah, *me'ilah*. You're not
allowed to eat from it because it's, you know, and it's, it's
קרבנות Korbanot. *korbanos* and you're not allowed, and it's a circumstance let's
say that it's even קדשי קדשים Kodshim *kodshei kodshim* and you're a
זר *zar*, so therefore you're not allowed to eat from, it might
be the כהנים kohanim, *Kohanim* were allowed to eat from it, you're
not, and therefore there's a sin of מעילה *me'ilah* as well, that
is an אשם *asham*. רבי מאיר אומר Rabbi Meir omer, אם היה
שבת Shabbos, והוציאו חייב chayav *Rabbi Meir omer im hayah Shabbos vehotzio
chayav*. Oh, I can get a sixth one. Let's say you were
chomping on your קדשים Kodshim *kodshim* sandwich and חלב chelev. *cheilev* קדשים
kodshim, *kodshim* sandwich and you were טמא *tamei* and you were going
ahead and it was שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*, so you were carrying it
out as you were walking in רשות reshus הרבים *reshus harabbim*. אמרו
לו *Amru lo*, they said to him, אינו מן השם *eino min
hasheim*. No, that's not because of eating, that's because of carrying. Yes,
it's at the same time. You know, you could also be doing
a different מלאכה Melacha, *melachah* with your hand, you could be lighting
a fire while you're eating, okay, but there it's not because of
eating, we're trying to say the eating itself. Actually, by the way,
I made a mistake, it's
חלב chelev *cheilev*, so nobody obviously is allowed to eat from it
when I, so anyway, you know, basically when I said the מעילה
*me'ilah* is, so it doesn't have to just be קדשי קדשים kodshim,
*kodshei kodshim*, it's חלב chelev. *cheilev*, so obviously it always goes on
the מזבח *mizbe'ach*, nobody's allowed to eat from it, so therefore obviously
there's going to be מעילה *me'ilah* as well. Let's take a look
at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
What's the point of this?
That's an interesting question. I would say the point is perhaps other
than sometimes maybe the rabbis just having fun, you know, trying to
like figure out, oh, how many, whatever, how many angels can dance
on the head of a pin type of thing. The גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* is going to frame it in the question of איסור חל
על איסור Issur Chal Al Issur *issur chal al issur*. That normally
we say that once something is אסור Assur *assur* one way, it
can't become doubly אסור Assur *assur*, and then we're going to say
why is this an exception to that rule? Okay, so and you
know, you could imagine a scenario where if you, where now you
say who cares about איסור חל על איסור Issur Chal Al Issur,
*issur chal al issur*, you're already bringing one קרבן korban *korban*. Well
no, because first of all there's implications, you actually do bring multiple
קרבנות Korbanot, *korbanos*. But the halachic principle it's telling you is is
that you don't say once it's אסור Assur *assur* once it can't
be multiply אסור Assur *assur* in an איסור חל על איסור Issur
Chal Al Issur *issur chal al issur* question, which is a pretty,
you know, general question that gets discussed or issue that gets discussed
throughout ש"ס *Shas*. So let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara*. נימא *Neima*, says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, נימא איתא דרבי מאיר
Meir. איסור חל על איסור Issur Chal Al Issur. *neima isei deRabbi
Meir issur chal al issur*. This sounds like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
*Rabbi Meir*, now why do we seize on רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir,
*Rabbi Meir*? Because he's the only named תנא Tanna, *Tanna* in this
משנה Mishnah? *Mishnah*. So really it means the author of the משנה
Mishnah. *Mishnah*, but at least the one we know is talking is
רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir... *Rabbi Meir*. So let's say רבי מאיר Rebbe
Meir *Rabbi Meir* holds איסור חל על איסור Issur Chal Al Issur.
*issur chal al issur*, that although it's אסור assur *assur* once you
can layer on איסורים issurim *issurim*, you don't say once it's אסור
assur *assur* it cannot become, you know, multiply אסור assur *assur*, this
object. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, ביה דאיסור חל על
איסור Issur לית ליה *behi de'issur chal al issur leifei*, we could
say in general he does not hold that one איסור Issur *issur*
can take place on another one. איסור כולל Issur Kolel ואיסור מוסיף
אית ליה *issur kolel ve'issur mosif is lei*. He does have though
the principle of כולל Kolel, *kolel* and מוסיף *mosif*. Now by the
way, איסור חל על איסור issur chal al issur, *issur chal al
issur* is really fundamentally an issue when it's one object becoming forbidden.
written multiple times. We don't say for example, like I said, if
I'm lighting a fire on שבת Shabbos? with one hand and I'm
doing some other מלאכה, melacha. you know, some other prohibition with another
hand, that's an איסור חל על איסור issur chal al issur, problem.
Even if I'm doing two separate acts with one hand, you know,
we don't say it's an איסור חל על איסור, issur chal al
issur I'm doing two separate things at the same time. איסור חל
על איסור issur chal al issur. is fundamentally about an object. This
object is already forbidden, can it become forbidden yet in another way?
Or do we say once it has a status of being forbidden,
it cannot be, you know, its status is already defined. It cannot
become doubly defined. So it's very object-based. Now, what is איסור כולל
Issur Kolel and איסור מוסיף? Issur Mosif? I wanted to bring a
marker but okay, it's not needed right away, but it might be
needed later. איסור כולל Issur Kolel. and איסור מוסיף Issur Mosif is
the following. They basically say if the new איסור Issur is of
broader scope, then because it makes other things forbidden, it can make
this forbidden in an additional way. Now, broader scope can be of
two ways. Broader scope can be the new איסור Issur is making
more objects forbidden. Not this object forbidden in new ways, but more
objects forbidden. What would be an example of that? An example of
that would be, well let's see, the גמרא Gemara will give it
right away. Let's read the first line of the גמרא. Gemara טהור
מעיקרא לא אסר אלא בחלב. Tahor Mi-kara Lo Assar Ela Be-chelev. So
let's say originally you were טהור Tahor and this fat was forbidden
to you because you're, but that's the only prohibition, fat, because you're
טהור, Tahor, there's not an additional prohibition. הוי ליה טמא, Havei Lei
Tamei, now you became טמא. So now what are you אסור assur
to you because you're טמא? All קרבנות. Korbanot. So מיגו דאיתסר בחתיכות
טהורות, Migo De-it-assar Be-chatichot Tehorot, since now you're forbidden in all טהור,
Tahor, you know, קדשים types of pieces of meat, of food, איתוסף
בינמי איסור עלוי דחלב. Itosef Beinammi Issur Alai De-chelev. So now the
איסור Issur is also added עלוי דחלב Alai De-chelev on top of
the חלב. chelev That is called an איסור כולל. Issur Kolel. Okay,
which is more objects become forbidden, so this becomes forbidden as well.
So it started being חלב, chelev that's forbidden to me, I became
טמא, I'm now אסור assur in all קרבנות, Korbanot, including this. Since
all things are being forbidden to me and there's an impact on
that status, that status of forbiddenness took effect now vis-a-vis all these
other objects, it also takes effect vis-a-vis this object. That's כולל, kolel
more objects are forbidden.
Now you bring it over twice then?
Yes, and you bring two קרבנות. korbanot Now what's an איסור מוסיף?
Issur Mosif? An איסור מוסיף Issur Mosif is this same thing, it's
only this object that's forbidden, but it's now forbidden to more people.
What would be an example of that? Let's keep on reading.
Like your sister, forbidden to you, then she gets married, forbidden to
everybody.
Right, that would be an example. Okay, so jumping to a different
example, which we're going to get to in a משנה, Mishnah right,
Michael gives an example, let's say my sister gets married. So before
she was just forbidden to me, now that she's married she's אסור
assur to all men other than her husband. So now she's also
אסור assur to me as a married woman, not just as my
sister. Okay, so that's the same thing is forbidden, but now it's
forbidden to more people. So more objects is an איסור כולל. Issur
Kolel The same thing to more people is an איסור מוסיף. Issur
Mosif. Either of those, you say איסור חל על איסור. Issur Chal
Al Issur Okay, so let's keep on reading in the גמרא. Gemara
וחלב, Ve-chelev,
now when you come to fat, fat, מעיקרא לא אסר אלא באכילה.
Mi-kara Lo Assar Ela Be-achila. Now this is a little bit problematic
because this doesn't exactly fit the normal mold. Let's read it though.
Originally fat is only forbidden to be eaten. אקדשיה, Akdeshei, you now
sanctified it. So מיגו דאיתוסף ביה איסור הנאה, Migo De-itosef Bei Issur
Hana'ah, איתוסף ביה לגבי חלב. Itosef Bei Legabei Chelev.
Now it is forbidden in a more weightier way. Before fat was
only forbidden to me to eat. Now that it's sanctified, it's, which
is a, which is now the איסור issur. of קרבנות, of מעילה,
right, deriving benefit from sanctified objects. So what's the הלכה Halacha of
not deriving benefit from sanctified objects? You can't even derive benefit, not
only you can't eat. So the fat was first forbidden to eat.
Now that it's sanctified and there's an איסור issur deriving benefit from
sanctified things, it's אסור בהנאה. Assur Be-hana'ah. So therefore that makes it
weightier. And because it's weightier, it can also become, they can get
that double status. Now that actually, that actually technically speaking is not
איסור כולל Issur Kolel, or איסור מוסיף. Issur Mosif. That actually is
a phrase that the גמרא Gemara calls איסור חמור. Issur Chamur. איסור
חמור Issur Chamur just means like it says, it's a weightier prohibition.
So it's the same object, right, it's forbidden to the same group
of people. Who's fat forbidden to? All Jews. Who are קדשים forbidden
to? All Jews. It's not forbidden to new people, it's not new
objects, I only sanctified this one piece of fat. Not new people,
not new objects, it's just that it's a weightier prohibition. It's also
forbidden in הנאה. Hana'ah. So that is actually called איסור חמור Issur
Chamur and the גמרא Gemara sometimes is skeptical whether that's enough to
say the second status takes effect. Here the גמרא Gemara is assuming
that it does. So there are three concepts: איסור כולל, issur kolel
more objects, like all קדשים are forbidden to me when I become
טמא; איסור מוסיף, Issur Mosif, more people are forbidden to this object,
we haven't seen that yet. Those are two classic exceptions to איסור
חל על איסור. Issur Chal Al Issur. Those are cases we will
say a second status will take effect. And now what we just
said, which is more, which is not so clear but the גמרא
Gemara here is assuming it, איסור חמור, Issur Chamur, a weightier prohibition.
The fat was forbidden to all Jews, now it becomes קדשים, it's
also same object, same people, but it's now more forbidden. It's forbidden
because you can't derive benefit, that this גמרא Gemara is assuming will
mean that the second status will take effect. You had a question,
Michael?
Well, because, you know, sometimes it's a little bit hard to differentiate
because you didn't just sanctify the חלב, chelev, you sanctified the whole
קרבן korban. and now more of the, you know, more of the
קרבן, the rest of the קרבן is forbidden.
Oh, yeah, that's an interesting point. Would we say that that makes
it איסור כולל issur kolel. because now in your act of sanctity
you affected the whole thing? Or do we sort of say that
that was—that's a good question, why the גמרא Gemara doesn't consider the
sanctifying to be that—you can't obviously just sanctify the חלב. chelev I
mean, you could as בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, but presumably here we're
talking about a קרבן.
It's an interesting question why we wouldn't consider that כולל because, you
know, you are in that same act. That's a good question, I
don't know. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay,
והשתא לגבי הדיוט הוא דאסור אבל לגבוה שרי. ve-hashta legabei hedyot hu
de-assur aval le-gavoha shari.
Now this fat you could put on the altar, right? It's forbidden
to all people including כהנים, but it's permissible to God, you could
put it on the altar, right? Then what happens? הוי ליה נותר,
havei lei notar, then you left it over till the next morning
and it became נותר. notar So מיגו דאיתוסף איסורא לגבי גבוה, migo
de-itosaf issura legabei gavoha,
now it's also אסור assur to God. Okay, so that's more people,
if you would. So now it's not only אסור assur to people,
it's also אסור assur? to put on the altar. So that affects
more, you know, the population it affects is bigger. So that's a
case
of איסור מוסיף. issur mosif. It affects a larger population. So therefore,
איתוסף ביה לגבי הדיוט, itosaf bei legabei hedyot, it's also additionally forbidden
to me. So it gets another level of being forbidden. Now, חל
עליה יום הכיפורים, chal aleih Yom HaKippurim, now it becomes יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur Now, by the way, יום כיפור Yom Kippur is very
bizarre to have in this conversation of איסור חל על איסור, Issur
Chal Al Issur? because יום כיפור Yom Kippur is not a status
about the object, right? יום כיפור Yom Kippur. is about like me,
the, you know, fasting or not fasting. The object is just the
means for me to break my fast. It's not like a forbidden
object. So it's always very strange when יום כיפור Yom Kippur. gets
thrown in here. I don't really have a good explanation. But anyway,
חל עליה יום הכיפורים, chal aleih Yom HaKippurim, then it becomes יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur מיגו דאיתוסף ביה איסורא לגבי חולין, migo de-itosaf bei
issura legabei chullin,
more objects are now forbidden on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur On יום
כיפור Yom Kippur all food is forbidden, not just this food. So
since more objects are forbidden, remember that's איסור כולל. issur kolel So
therefore, איתוסף ביה לגבי גבוה. itosaf bei legabei gavoha.
So therefore it's also forbidden in new ways to God, to me,
it has all these additional—you know, this other status gets added on.
So again,
when can you say a new status of forbidden status can take
effect on top? Everybody agrees if it's an איסור כולל issur kolel
or pretty much everybody if it's איסור כולל issur kolel or איסור
מוסיף. issur mosif. איסור כולל Issur Kolel. is the new status makes
more objects forbidden. Examples for that would be יום כיפור Yom Kippur
or which makes all food forbidden, becoming טמא which makes all קרבנות
forbidden. That's new objects are forbidden. Or איסור מוסיף, issur mosif, more—a
bigger population is forbidden. Like when it becomes נותר, notar. it's also
forbidden to God. A larger population is forbidden. Then you have the
final example which the גמרא Gemara is throwing into this mix but
is not always thrown in, which is איסור חמור. issur chamur. It's
a more weightier prohibition, like when it became חלב chelev and then
becomes קדשים, it's the same population, the same object, but it is
now also forbidden because—but it's weightier because it's forbidden בהנאה. be-hana'ah. So
those are the exceptions to איסור חל על איסור, issur chal al
issur? and that's how you can have the cases in our משנה.
Mishnah Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara. goes on, says the following.
So ורמינהו u-reminhu איסור חל על איסור issur chal al issur that
people don't hold by that. Everyone—no one would hold by that.
Well, we'll have them, okay, so don't worry, the discussion isn't over.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. But it could
be obvious. Let's say something that is a נבילה, neveilah, well, okay.
If you make a נבילה בשר בחלב neveilah basar be-chalav and you
don't hold of איסור חמור, issur chamur, then that wouldn't be, because
it's just אסור assur. to the same people, same object, it's just
now weightier because it's also forbidden בהנאה. be-hana'ah. I mean, you could
have another case of—what would you have a case of?
So anyway, but you're saying חמור chamur is weightier.
Let's say I take—so let's say I take נותר nosar, which is
אסור כרת assur kares and I also cook it in milk. Okay,
so it's not weightier, it's not more people, it's not more object,
so that would not become an איסור בשר בחלב. issur basar be-chalav.
The issue, by the way, about נבילה בשר בחלב neveilah basar be-chalav
is an important question for dog food. Because if you
take—בשר בחלב basar be-chalav does not apply to non-kosher meat in the
sense of non-beef, you know, whatever, non-chicken. But if you take beef
that's just a נבילה, neveilah, not שחוטה shechutah properly, and you cook
it in milk, which is often what they do in dog food,
okay, is it becomes also בשר בחלב basar be-chalav and then it
becomes אסור בהנאה, assur be-hana'ah, you can't feed it to your dog
or cat because it's אסור בהנאה. assur be-hana'ah. So that actually is
an important question. Anyway, moving on.
So there are some practical—so you're dealing with the case you said
before,
the נותר nosar.
that you made בשר בחלב. basar be-chalav.
Right, so no one would say that it's over twice, you're just
over on נותר. nosar, Right.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. וניתי הך חטאת, ve-neitei hach chatat,
wait, I can get—I can up the number instead of... Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says like this. וניתני ה חטאות *V'nisni
hei chataos*. Wait! I can get- I can up the number! Instead
of four חטאות *chataos* and one אשם *asham*, אשם מעילה *asham me'ilah*,
you'd get five חטאות *chataos*. How? ונוקמה כגון דאכל כזית kezayit. פיגול
pigul בחדא כזית kezayit. פיגול pigul. *V'nukma kegon d'achal kezayis pigul
b'chada kezayis pigul*. So maybe I have this one כזית kezayit? *kezayis*
of forbidden fat, that I'm getting four plus one, and in the
same chewing I'm also eating the כזית kezayit, *kezayis* of פיגול pigul
*pigul*. Okay, פיגול pigul. *pigul* remember is a קרבן *korban* that I
thought to eat at the wrong time, whatever, and that's also כרת
*kareis*. That's a strange question because that's a totally separate type of
an object. The same object can't be פיגול pigul *pigul* and נותר
nosar *nosar*. Once it's פיגול pigul. *pigul* and it's not fit for
being put on the מזבח *mizbeiach*, it can't become נותר notar, *nosar*,
right? נותר *nosar* is that it was fit for being put on
the altar and left over. So something that's פיגול pigul *pigul* can't
be נותר *nosar*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is talking about a
separate כזית kezayit *kezayis*. Once you're talking about a separate כזית kezayit.
*kezayis*, why don't we also say and I'm also chewing חמץ chametz
בפסח *chametz b'Pesach* and דם *dam*? And then you could ask- well
that at least it would be eaten though. Okay, so it's a
strange question and that's essentially what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going
to answer, that we're talking about the same object, we're not different
objects. So let's take a look. But that's going to sort of
get the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* involved in that for for the rest
of mostly the rest of the page. So let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
so it says like this, בחדא בהמה קאמרי בשתי בהמות לא קאמרי
*B'chada beheima ka'amri b'shtei beheimos lo ka'amri*. We're talking about one animal.
Okay, and the same animal if it's פיגול pigul. *pigul* cannot become
נותר *nosar*. So because once it's not fit for the altar it
won't become נותר *nosar*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, ונותר ופיגול בחדא בהמה לא משכחת
לה *V'nosar u'pigul b'chada beheima lo mishkachas lah*. And you can't have
נותר *nosar* and פיגול pigul *pigul* in one בהמה *beheima* because once
it's not fit for the altar, it's פיגול pigul, *pigul*, it won't
become נותר *nosar*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אלא לאו *Ela
lav*, why not? משכחת לה כגון דהעלה אבר פיגול pigul. *Mishkachas lah
kegon d'he'ela eiver pigul*. Let's say you made your animal פיגול pigul,
*pigul*. You slaughtered it and planned to eat it at the wrong
time. And then what did you do? You took one of the
limbs like a big leg of the cow לגבי מזבח *legabei mizbeiach*
and you put it on the altar. You're not supposed to, it's
פיגול *pigul*, but you went ahead and did it or a כהן
Kohen, *kohen* did it. Now what's the הלכה halacha *halacha*? Once it
is put on the altar דפקע פיגוליה מיניה *depaka pigulei minei*. It
loses its status of פיגול *pigul* והוי ליה נותר vehave le nosar,
*v'havei lei nosar*. And then it could become נותר *nosar*. Actually this
was a רש"י Rashi *Rashi* in last week's פרשה *parsha*, right, זאת
תורת העולה היא העולה על מוקדה על המזבח כל הלילה עד הבוקר
*Zos toras ha'olah hi ha'olah al mokdah al hamizbeiach kol halailah ad
haboker*. Actually רש"י Rashi *Rashi* in last week's פרשה *parsha* was quoted
a lot of stuff we've learned, you know, whatever, in the last
few months. Anyway, כל העולים *kol ha'olim*, anything that is put on
the altar, once it's put on the altar, even if it's פסול
*pasul*, don't take it off. Okay, so if you put a פיגול
*pigul* on the altar, even though it was פסול *pasul*, it stays
on the altar, you don't take it off. And therefore, let's say,
so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s understanding, let's say it won't be נותר
*nosar*. Okay, but let's say it was put on the altar and
fell off. Now what's the status? Does it re-become פיגול *pigul* or
the fact that it was on the altar and allowed to stay
means that it loses its status? If it lost its status of
פיגול *pigul* and then it fell off, now it would become נותר
*nosar* if you leave it over. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*'s
assuming that once it's on the altar it loses its status of
פיגול *pigul*, that and therefore you keep it on, and therefore even
if it falls off, it remains non-פיגול *pigul* and can become נותר
*nosar*. So you can get נותר *nosar* in the same piece that
you also have פיגול *pigul*. What? And then you should put it
back up, which is a pretty surprising idea, but let's take a
look.
So the גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* says, once it's פיגול *pigul*- so the
answer is it's-
but the point is but then it's no longer פיגול *pigul*, you're
still not going to get both. Okay, don't worry, we're getting there.
Okay, but let's take a look. אבר פיגול *Eiver pigul*- so כגון
דהעלה אבר פיגול לגבי מזבח דפקע פיגוליה מיניה *kegon d'he'ela eiver pigul
legabei mizbeiach depaka pigulei minei*. It stops being פיגול *pigul* והוי ליה
נותר *v'havei lei nosar*. And then it can become נותר *nosar*. וכדאמר
עולא *U'k'de'amar Ulla*, like עולא *Ulla* says, קומץ פיגול שהעלה לגבי מזבח
*Kometz pigul she'he'ela legabei mizbeiach*. You have a קומץ *kometz* of the
מנחה *mincha*, the hand-breadth of the מנחה *mincha* that was פיגול *pigul*.
And now you put it on the altar. פקע פיגוליה ממנו *Paka
pigulei mimenu*. It stops being פיגול *pigul* והוי ליה נותר *v'havei lei
nosar*. And then it becomes נותר *nosar* if it comes off. Now,
as Michael says, but of course if it's no longer פיגול *pigul*
because and now it's נותר *nosar*, then you're still not getting both.
But the idea is like this. The whole animal was פיגול *pigul*.
You planned to do the whole animal in the wrong time. So
the whole animal became פיגול *pigul*. Then you put one limb on
the altar, it stopped being פיגול *pigul*, fell off, you waited a
day, it became נותר *nosar*. Now I can eat a כזית kezayit
*kezayis* from that limb which is נותר *nosar* and a כזית kezayit
*kezayis* from another part of the animal which was never on the
altar, only one limb was on the altar, and this will be
נותר *nosar*, this will be פיגול *pigul*, and it'll all be from
the same animal. Do you got the scenario? So I can
eat- it's not different animals. Half of the animal lost its status
of פיגול *pigul* because it was put on the altar, that became
נותר *nosar*, the rest was not put on the altar. So I'm
eating two כזיתים kezayitim, *kezaysim* and I'm getting another
חטאת *chatas*. You could- I was thinking about that. You could still
say דם *dam*, right. So the obvious point is we're trying to
get not just the same animal but the same object, which is
eventually where the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to get to. Let's keep
on going.
אכילה אחת *Achilah achas*... you mean like...
well that's where- that's where it's getting. So let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, באבר אחד קאמרי בשני אברים לא
קאמרי *B'eiver echad ka'amri b'shnei evarim lo ka'amri*. So we're not boiling
it down yet to a כזית kezayit *kezayis*, we're saying one limb
yes, not two limbs. So that would be two separate limbs. ונותר
ופיגול בחד אבר לא משכחת לה *V'nosar u'pigul b'chad eiver lo mishkachas
lah*. You cannot get both נותר *nosar* and פיגול *pigul* in the
same limb. So of course that's just a setup because you know,
אלא לאו *ela lav*, why not? משכחת לה כגון דהעלה אבר פיגול
לגבי מזבח *Mishkachas lah kegon d'he'ela eiver pigul legabei mizbeiach*. You took
this same limb, you put it on the altar, that was פיגול
*pigul*, okay, but of course you didn't put the whole limb on
the altar, right? Only part of it was on the fire, part
of it was dangling over the edge or not on the fire.
Exactly where you define the line, okay, but what do you do?
פלגי אבר על גבי מזבח פלגי מאבראי *Palgei eiver al gabei mizbeiach
palgei me'avra'ei*. Half of it was on the altar, half of it
was outside. of the altar דמזבח, דו דמזבח פסקה פיגול du demizbeach
paska pigul והוי ליה נותר, the fact the half that was on
the altar stopped being פיגול and then if it fell off will
become נותר, and the other half remained פיגול. So you can have
a כזית kezayit from two halves of a limb. But that's the
Gemara's thinking. Let's see what the Gemara's answering. So that half of
the limb stops being פיגול and can later become נותר. The other
half is פיגול. So you can have from the same limb and
you can get an additional prohibition. So Gemara says, דהוא ד... dehu
de... okay, ואמר עולא, ve'amar ulla, so Gemara says, ואמר עולא אמר,
ve'amar ulla amar, קומץ פיגול שהעלה על גבי המזבח פסקה פיגול ממנו
והוי ליה נותר. kometz pigul shehe'elo al gabbei hamizbeach paska pigul mimenu
vehave le nosar. Okay,
once again quoting Ulla that it stops being פיגול once it's put
on the altar. אמר ליה לא. amar leh lo. No. Make up
your mind. אי רובא דמזבח שדי ליה למזבח. i rubba demizbeach shadye
leh lemizbeach. Where is the majority of the limb? If the majority
of it is on the altar, you consider it all on the
altar and it all changes status. רובא דבראי שדי ליה לבראי, rubba
devarai shadye leh levrai, if the majority is off the altar, שדי
ליה לבראי. shadye levrai. So then consider it all off the altar.
You're not going to be able to split it and say half
yes, half no. It'll go by the majority. Now, of course, what
if it's exactly 50%? So at least now we're considering, assuming אי
אפשר לצמצם. iy efshar letzamtzem. Okay, we're assuming that it's got to
be majority one way. So the Gemara says, תפשוט דבעי רמי בר
חמא. tifshot deba'ei rami bar chama. So this... okay, I hear that,
that that's your answer, but that would force us to resolve a
question of Rami bar Chama. What was Rami bar Chama's question? Here's
what Rami bar Chama asked: הולכו באיברים אחר הרוב או לא? holchu
be'eivarim achar harov o lo? He wanted to know exactly this question.
If the majority of a limb is on the altar, do you
define the whole limb by the majority? So what was your response
to me? Your response was you can't have the limb half and
half because it'll go by the majority. Okay, I hear that answer,
but Rami bar Chama was, you know, had that as an open
question. Would you define the limb that's half on the altar by
the majority or not? Your answer assumes you would. To me, that
Rami bar Chama, that's not so clear. Maybe it wouldn't go by
the majority. And if it doesn't go by the majority, you're back
to your question that you can get, you know,
two prohibitions from the same limb. Half, you know, half נותר, half
פיגול. So why did that... wasn't that in the משנה? Mishnah So
the Gemara says, finally it's going to limit it down even more
than a limb to one כזית. kezayit So let's see what the
Gemara says. בכזית אחד קמיירי בשני זיתים לא קמיירי. bekezayit echad kama'iri
bishnei zeitim lo kama'iri. That's obviously where it was going to say,
okay, fine. But you could have... you could have one כזית kezayit
of one thing in this mouth and one כזית kezayit of another
thing in the other... in the other part of the mouth. But
in the same כזית, kezayit. that same minimum unit of forbidden food,
you're not going to get more than what we listed in our
משנה. Mishnah. If you want to also have פיגול or חמץ or
דם or whatever else you want to have, that is a separate
כזית. kezayit It is not the same כזית. kezayit Okay, so now
the Gemara says, ולא? velo? One minute. There is a reason we
were avoiding that answer. Is it really true that we're only talking
about one
כזית? kezayit והתניא יום הכפורים. veha tanya yom hakippurim. We taught Yom
Kippur. וביום הכפורים
כותבת מחייב. uveyom hakippurim kosevet mechayev. On Yom Kippur you don't transgress
by just eating a כזית, kezayit right? Yom Kippur is about fasting
and afflicting your soul. And we say that that's only considered negated
when you eat כותבת, kosevet, the amount of a pressed... I keep
on forgetting if it's a fig or a date. I think it's
date. A pressed date. Anyway, so which is about... which is two
כזיתים. kezayitim,
Okay, so therefore our כזית kezayit is really small. I know. I
know. Whatever. What's-his-name has a whole long thing about כזית. Yes. Anyway,
וכותבת אית בה שני זיתים. vechosevet it bei shnei zeitim. And we
know that a כותבת kosevet has minimally two כזיתים. kezaysim So you
can't get out of it so easily. Our משנה Mishnah. is anyway
talking about two כזיתים. kezaysim, Once it's talking about two כזיתים, kezaysim.
right, then you should have... you should be able to talk about
another prohibition. So the Gemara says, אמר רב זבירא כגון דאכל כוליה
בחלבא. amar rav zevira kegon de'achal kulya bechelva. Okay, what we're talking
about is that you... yes, it's two כזיתים, kezaysim. but it's all
one unit. You ate a kidney with its חלב. chelev So the
חלב chelev part is a כזית and that's all the prohibitions. And
what makes it enough for Yom Kippur is there's also a kidney
part. Now that's not exactly clear why that answers the question. So
let the חלב chelev be the... the נותר and let the kidney
be the פיגול. But the Gemara presumably is saying, you know, let
me just check how רש"י Rashi explains it. The next answers will
be a little bit clearer.
One minute. Right where the רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom starts. Yes. ואי
בעית אימא דאכל כוליה בחלבא דאכלי משום
פיגול ואכלי משום נותר למה לא תנא בחלבא
עצמו.
ve'i ba'it eima de'achal kulya bechelva de'achlei mishum pigul ve'achlei mishum
nosar
lama lo tana bechelva atzmo.
Right, so רש"י just says we're talking about one type of food.
You know, that the Gemara takes it for granted since we say
you could eat a כזית of חלב, chelev. that we're talking about
that the חלב has the prohibitions. So of course you'll say, okay,
but the whole חלב doesn't have the prohibition of Yom Kippur. But
at least it's part of the transgression of Yom Kippur. If we
were talking about a כזית of חלב and a כזית of kidney,
and that's why you transgress, so for all the prohibitions including Yom
Kippur, the eating of the חלב is part of that. Whereas if
you wanted to also throw in the idea that you also ate
פיגול and the kidney was פיגול, then the eating of the חלב
would not be part of the prohibition of what you got the
פיגול. The next answer is a little bit clearer along those lines.
Let's take the next answer. רב פפא אמר כגון דמליה בתמרי. Rav
Pappa amar kegon d'maliye b'tamrei. Oh! We're talking about let's say you
had already eaten a כזית of a date. Okay, so right now
you're just eating the כזית of חלב. Okay, right now you don't...
what's violating יום כיפור Yom Kippur is that it was this כזית
plus some food that you ate a little bit before. But in
this one eating, you're only eating a כזית. Okay, and this one
is enough to make you over on יום כיפור Yom Kippur, because
of what you ate before. רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda bar
Ahava okay fine. So whatever we got out of it, we pointed
out that yes, you could do multiple... you could be doing multiple
things in your mouth at the same time, but for one act
of eating you're only going to get four plus one, you're not
going to get more. Now, רב אדא בר אהבה מתני הכי חמש.
Rav Adda bar Ahava matni hachi chamesh. He actually has his... his
משנה Mishnah, actually did say five חטאות, not four.
ומתרץ כגון דאכל כזית פיגול U'metaretz kegon d'achal kezayit pigul and he
actually says like we were resisting all along, he says yes, it
one כזית was פיגול, one כזית was... was נותר, like the thing
that was half on the altar.
ולא משני כאני שינויי דקמשנינן V'lo m'shani kani shinuyei d'kam'shaninan and he
doesn't give the answers we gave before. Fine. So he actually had
an example where there were actually two separate כזיתים kezaysim in your
mouth. So now the גמרא Gemara says, ah, well, now that we're
willing to consider other things, extraneous things according to this גירסא girsa
of five, now we ask the questions we've been asking. וניתני שש
חטאות ונוקמה כגון דאכל כזית דם, V'nisni sheish chata'ot v'nokma kegon d'achal
kezayit dam, why don't we say six once we're talking about that
actually get a כזית of blood in your mouth as well? בחדא
אכילה קאמרי בשתי אכילות לא קאמרי. B'chada achila ka'amrei b'shtei achilot lo
ka'amrei. No, we're only talking about one act of eating, not two.
ושיערו חכמים דאין בית הבליעה מחזיק יותר משני זיתים. V'shi'uru chachamim d'ein
beit habli'ah machazik yoter mishnei zeisim. And you... and when you swallow,
which is part of eating, maybe you can chew more than two
כזיתים, but at one time you can't swallow more than two כזיתים.
So at most we could be talking about two כזיתים. So anyway,
that is just... again, we're just no longer, you know, like Rivka
said before, what's the practical הלכה of this? Not much, but now
that we're talking about this, we're trying to figure out how many
can we get? So in the same one כזית you can only
get this four plus one, but that assumes the case of יום
כיפור Yom Kippur, that you ate something beforehand. If we want to
talk about other things that you're also eating, then you could put
in another כזית and get some more, but more than two כזיתים
in one swallow you're not going to get. Now we get to
the final point that רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir says, what about if
he was doing it on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur. then he also
gets... on שבת, Shabbos? excuse me, then he also gets one for
carrying. And they said, yeah, we're not talking about carrying, we're talking
about eating. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, אומר, וניתני אם הוציאו חייב, v'nisni
im hotzio chayav, we'll just say look, if we already said it's
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur right, that was one of the prohibitions, eating
on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So why don't... why do we say
if it was שבת Shabbos, and you carried it? Why not just
say if you walked... walked with this outside in the street? Right,
why do you have to add the fact that it's שבת? Shabbos,
It's already יום כיפור Yom Kippur. and not allowed to carry on
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. מאי טעמא דקתני היתה שבת? Mai ta'ama d'katani
hayta Shabbos? Why did he qualify by saying if it's
שבת? Shabbos? אמר רפרם Amar Rafram זאת אומרת עירוב והוצאה לשבת ואין
עירוב והוצאה ליום הכיפורים. zot omeret eiruv v'hotza'ah l'Shabbos v'ein eiruv v'hotza'ah
l'Yom HaKippurim. And he says a pretty radical idea. You know what?
There's no איסור הוצאה issur hotza'ah on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur, Now,
that sounds completely radical to us. Okay, but remember that there's no
איסור הוצאה issur of hotza'ah basically on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Now
on יום טוב, Yom Tov, I should take a step back and
say the following. Why are certain מלאכות melachot מותר mutar on יום
טוב? Yom Tov? There's two conceptual models. One that we're most nominally
taught is the idea of אוכל נפש, ochel nefesh, things that you're
doing for the sake of food. Okay, obviously that would not be
relevant on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. A, the תורה Torah doesn't say
it on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, B, you don't eat on יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. Okay, but you might be aware that when we...
that if I were to ask you is carrying אסור assur on
יום טוב, Yom Tov, your probably gut answer would be no. You
wouldn't say, it's אסור assur but you're allowed to carry for the
sake of food. Do we ever think about that? No, we just
carry on יום טוב, Yom Tov, right? On... excuse me, on יום
טוב. Yom Tov. Fire also is an interesting question, right? If I
ask you is fire אסור assur on יום טוב, Yom Tov, you
probably wouldn't say yes, but if you can use it somehow for
the sake of food or מיגו migu or some other thing. No,
instinctively we think fire actually isn't אסור assur on יום טוב. Yom
Tov. And actually there's some basis for saying that in the גמרא.
Gemara That carrying and fire are in a separate category. They are
not just מותר mutar because of for the sake of food, they
might be more categorically מותר. mutar. It's actually interesting to note that
both of them have... are the two that are the most explicit
prohibitions in the תורה. Torah. לא תבערו אש בכל משבתיכם ביום השבת,
Lo tivaru eish b'chol moshvoteichem b'yom haShabbos, and carrying not really, but
carrying is learned out by it says by... you know, משה Moshe
says, you know, don't, you know, that... לא תוציאו... lo taitzi'u... no,
not לא תוציאו ממקומו, lo taitzi'u mimkomo,
but when they're bringing the... the stuff for the... מלאכת המשכן, melachat
haMishkan, you know, and so anyway, so they learn it out from
different פסוקים. pesukim. Anyway, so it could be that let's bracket fire
for now, it's not our interest, that הוצאה hotza'ah is generally called
by the ראשונים Rishonim as a מלאכה גרועה, melacha gerua, as a
not full מלאכה. melacha Now you're completely חייב מיתה, chayav mita, you're
completely prohibited and so on, but the reason it's not the classic
מלאכה melacha is because it's the one מלאכה melacha that is not
creative and productive. It's just transferring from one space to another. So
it could be that by יום טוב, Yom Tov, the idea that
it's permissible is not just... for the sake of אוכל נפש, ochel
nefesh, but it could be it's more categorically permissible because it was
the weakest of the מלאכות melachos to begin with. Given that possible
background, let's talk about יום כיפור, Yom Kippur. where nobody is suggesting
you can make a fire on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur Okay, that
is much more a fundamental מלאכה based on the idea of food
and so on. But if carrying is not because of food, carrying
is just because if it's not שבת, Shabbos, it's the first to
go, okay, and therefore יום טוב Yom Tov is a weaker קדושה,
kedusha, it's the first to go. So maybe it should also go
on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. But of course Michael says, but okay,
יום כיפור Yom Kippur. is also called שבת, Shabbos it's not just
a יום טוב, Yom Tov, it's שבת שבתון. Shabbos Shabbason. Fine, so
we're going to reject it. But I'm trying to explain to you
why the גמרא Gemara could have a הוה אמינא hava amina that
carrying is מותר mutar on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur And that's what
the גמרא Gemara. says. You know why רב מאיר Reb Meir says
שבת? Shabbos. Because actually carrying is biblically מותר mutar on יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur... Radical idea, that's what he says.
So we're talking about you carry for the sake of food? I
mean what was it?
No, on יום כיפור Yom Kippur. you can't carry at all unless
it's מאיר. No, we basically say, this is not, we're not learning
ביצה, Beitzah, but basically we say, I mean there's a debate of
בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, we basically say
you have to have some minimal reason to carry, but carrying is
pretty categorically permissible on יום כיפור... Yom Kippur on יום טוב. Yom
Tov. Okay, although there is some debate, don't take that להלכה l'halacha
because there is some question about maybe needing some minimal justification. But
it's a very low-level minimal justification. By fire, for example, there's even
a discussion, are you allowed to be מדליק נר של בטלה, madlik
ner shel batala, a light with no purpose at all? So those
two are really questions, how much justification? Yeah, you know, you're carrying
over a bottle of wine to my house, you have to carry
from one רשות to another, to... but we're not learning יום טוב
Yom Tov right now. Just for now accept that that is something
that might not be food-related.
You can't carry away your used dirty tissue which you're not going
to use again.
Right, okay, anyway, but let's take a look. The question is, is
that דאורייתא? d'Oraisa? דרבנן? d'Rabanan? Anyway, okay, so אמר רפרם, Amar Rafram,
זאת אומרת עירוב הוצאה לשבת ואין עירוב הוצאה ליום הכיפורים. zos omeres
eiruv hotza'ah l'Shabbos v'ein eiruv hotza'ah l'Yom HaKippurim.
Now why he says עירוב eiruv is a little funny, but presumably
it means that that's, you know, there's different ways of explaining what
עירוב eiruv means, but in this context, but we'll just say the
rabbinic needs of עירוב eiruv because there are prohibitions of הוצאה hotza'ah
on שבת, Shabbos, ואין עירוב הוצאה ליום הכיפורים, v'ein eiruv hotza'ah l'Yom
HaKippurim, but biblically it is not an issue on יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur, ממאי? Mimai? How do you know that's true? דילמא יש עירוב
הוצאה ליום הכיפורים, Dilma yesh eiruv hotza'ah l'Yom HaKippurim, and maybe it
is prohibited.
והכי קתני, V'hachi katani, אם הוציא בשבת הוציא חייב אף משום שבת.
im hotzi b'Shabbos hotzi chayav af mishum Shabbos. Since רב מאיר Reb
Meir is just trying to up the numbers, yeah, he could have
said if you carried there on יום כיפור Yom Kippur, it's another
חטאת. But he's trying to get yet another one, so add שבת
Shabbos. and you get two more חטאות. One for carrying on יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur one for carrying on שבת. Shabbos? ויום... אף משום
שבת ויום הכיפורים. af mishum Shabbos v'Yom HaKippurim. אלא אי איתמר דרפרם
אהא דתניא איתמר. Ella i itmar d'Rafram aha d'tanya itmar. So if
רפרם's Rafram statement was said to try to argue that there's no
איסור דאורייתא issur d'Oraisa biblically of carrying on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur.
it was said on the following statement.
דתניא, Detanya, ושלח ביד איש עתי. v'shilach b'yad ish iti. This is
sending the שעיר לעזאזל, se'ir l'Azazel, you should send it by a
ready man, right, to the wilderness. איש, Ish, להכשיר את הזר, l'hachshir
es hazar, any man, it doesn't even have to be a כהן,
Kohen. even a non-כהן. עתי, Iti, ready, prepared, אפילו בטומאה. afilu b'tumah.
Even in
somehow we learn from that, anybody, even somebody that is טמא, אפילו
בשבת, afilu b'Shabbos, and even on שבת, Shabbos? you can go ahead
and send this out, send out the שעיר לעזאזל. se'ir l'Azazel. עתי
במזומן קתני. Iti b'mezuman katani. במזומן. b'mezuman. Okay, במזומן, b'mezuman, and the
עתי iti means that he has to be ready, he has to
be designated ahead of time. Now, קתני עתי אפילו בשבת. katani iti
afilu b'Shabbos. So it says though one of the things it's coming
to לחדש l'chadesh here is that you can send out the שעיר
לעזאזל se'ir l'Azazel even on שבת. Shabbos? So אמר רפרם, amar Rafram,
זאת אומרת עירוב הוצאה לשבת ואין עירוב הוצאה ליום
הכיפורים. zos omeres eiruv hotza'ah l'Shabbos v'ein eiruv hotza'ah l'Yom HaKippurim. Why
you have to tell me, oh, you can do it on שבת?
Shabbos? What's new by שבת? Shabbos? I mean, what are you doing
anyway by carrying this goat out? And mostly what you're doing is
some carrying, it's even not clear how you're carrying, maybe you're just
running with it, but let's say you had to pick it up
and carry it, whatever, you could imagine that there's some carrying that
might go along with that. Or maybe you have to take some
water or whatever, but that's another יום כיפור Yom Kippur issue. Anyway,
but he says, so the only, why add שבת? Shabbos Whatever you're
doing, you're already allowing on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur, Why do you
need to also allow the fact that it's שבת? Shabbos So ממאי,
mimai, and so
why does it say you're allowed on שבת? Shabbos It must be
because on יום כיפור Yom Kippur you're not prohibited to carry, and
it's telling you even if it's שבת Shabbos. and even if you're
prohibited to carry, you're still allowed to carry if it's necessary for
sending the שעיר se'ir out. So the גמרא Gemara says ממאי? mimai?
How do you know that? שבת שאני שעיר משתלח דאכשר ביום הכיפורים
בכך. shabbos shani se'ir mishtale'ach d'achshar b'Yom HaKippurim bekach.
Since this goat was sent out, it's part of the עבודה avodah
of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur it's obvious we would allow the יום
כיפור Yom Kippur. prohibitions. It's not obvious we would allow external prohibitions.
So of course יום כיפור Yom Kippur could be forbidden in carrying
and of course we would allow it for the sake of the
שעיר, se'ir, but it doesn't mean we would violate שבת Shabbos prohibitions
even though they're the exact same, because it's because this is about
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So יום כיפור Yom Kippur? things are allowed,
שבת Shabbos, things are not allowed. אלא דרפרם ברותי. Ella d'Rafram brusi.
So rather the statement of רפרם Rafram is nonsense. I mean, that's
actually a pretty harsh word in גמרא, Gemara. it's a joke, it's
nonsense. So although actually actually seems that it's not a crazy read
of our משנה Mishnah, of רבי מאיר, you know, the גמרא rejects
that. Of course carrying is אסור assur on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur,
Okay, but again the הוה אמינא Havamina is fascinating. It points to
the fact that the permission of carrying on יום טוב Yom Tov
is not just based on food, right? That the permission of carrying
on יום טוב Yom Tov has to it might be based on
the fact that it's just not שבת. Shabbos. Not שבת Shabbos carrying
is permitted, permissible. So then what about יום כיפור? Yom Kippur On
the one hand it's not שבת, on the other hand it's called
שבת. But the גמרא completely rejects it. Sorry, carrying is forbidden on
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur no more discussion. Okay, so now we get
on to the next משנה.
Mishnah Because of יום כיפור Yom Kippur or because it's rejecting that
idea of dropping carrying on יום טוב? Yom Tov?
Oh, so meaning meaning is it because of it thinks that יום
כיפור is like שבת or because it thinks that carrying is about
food? Right, so that's a good question. So that we'll talk about
when we learn מסכת ביצה. Masechet Beitzah. But I'm just telling you
where the הוה אמינא Havamina is coming from. It's not a crazy
הוה אמינא. Havamina. Okay, let's take a look at the משנה. Mishnah
יש ביאה אחת. Yesh biah achas. Now that we're done with eating,
now we get to sex. Somebody can have one act of sex,
okay, וחייב עליה שש חטאות, vechayav aleha shesh chataos, and get six
sin offerings. Okay, כיצד? Keitzad? Right. הבא על בתו. Haba al bito.
Now we're going to have these crazy cases. It's going to look
like learning יבמות. Yevamos. Okay everybody, let's bathe. הבא על בתו, Haba
al bito,
so a man had sex with his daughter.
Where does it say that's אסור? assur Where does it...
it doesn't. It says actually בת בתו. bas bito. It says אשה
ובתה, ishah uvitah, so if it's his wife, it says it's אסור.
Assur If it's his daughter that's not from his wife, then the
גמרא learns it out. Actually we had that earlier in the מסכת.
masechet.
It doesn't say father and daughter in the תורה.
Torah. It speaks about granddaughter. It says it does not say explicitly
daughter. The גמרא learns it out. Okay, it's not explicit in the
תורה. Torah. Okay, so with one's daughter, so חייב עליה משום בתו,
chayav aleha mishum bito, daughter, ואחות אשתו ואחותו, veachot ishto veachoto, his
sister. Now how do you have a daughter who is also your
sister? So we have to basically assume that this man had sex
with his mother and had a daughter. So this daughter is his
daughter, but it's also his mother's daughter, so it's his daughter and
his sister. Okay, so we already have to assume that bizarre case.
And why is the mother not a separate case?
Because that was a separate act. We're talking about one act. That
was something you did that was prohibited, but that was, you know,
ten years ago, whatever it was. Okay, fine. Right, exactly.
Okay, now ואחותו, veachoto, so sister, אשת אחיו, eshet achiv, his brother's
wife, which means that this woman that he married his brother. Now
his brother was allowed to marry her because it's his daughter, so
it's his brother's niece, right? The brother can marry his niece, so
that was a binding קידושין. kiddushin. Then his brother divorced her or
died. So that prohibition remains even after the brother's no longer married.
So it's also now his brother's wife. ואשת אחי אביו. ve'eshet achi
aviv. Now after his brother divorced her, his father's brother, his uncle
married her. That was his... so that was the man's grandniece, right?
His uncle married this woman, right, this his daughter. So an uncle
marrying a great-uncle marrying a great-niece. Okay, so that was a permissible
marriage. Then the great-uncle died. So now it's forbidden not only as
his brother's sister, but as his brother's wife, but as his uncle's
wife. ואשת איש, ve'eshet ish, and now she maybe she's still married
to that uncle or she's married to a third guy, so she's
a married woman. ונדה, veniddah, and she's a נדה. niddah. Okay, so
you have all of those six כריתות in that one bizarre case.
Only only one of them had came through having pursued with an
איסור. issur The fact that it was both his sister and his
daughter.
So if your whole point was אין איסור חל על איסור, ein
issur chal al issur, then what do we really need to do
all these other cases?
Okay, because the גמרא is now going to play it out that
maybe it's not all so explicit. So let's take a look. Each
case has to be spelled out. Let's take a look. I really
think the answer is it's not just to teach you אין איסור
חל על איסור, ein issur chal al issur, but that the גמרא
was like, you know, that חז"ל Chazal were having a little fun.
Like they were trying to figure it out to say that, you
know, if you're already getting that, like meaning that oh and then
he had sex with his mother and, you know what I mean?
Then you can say and they also
whatever, you can always add on. I understand. Not all because it's
it's like it's a fun game. How many different איסורים issurim can
you imagine could occur in one case? Somebody said somebody said once,
he says, you know, what do you think they did before they
had TV? You know, they said, okay, how many different ways...
maybe they did it on יום כיפור or something.
We're trying to do it because of that's not a חייב כרת.
chayav kares. Sex is not a חייב כרת. chayav kares.
There's a difference between joking about eating the food and sleeping with
your daughter.
Now I'm
not
say... so fine. I said that maybe they were doing it as
a type of a puzzle and a mind game. We don't know
why. It's not so funny. I understand. You're absolutely right. Point well
taken. I stand corrected. I mean or whatever, point well taken. So
now the גמרא says like this. והא לית ליה לרבי מאיר איסור
חל על איסור. Veha leis lei leRebbe Meir issur chal al issur.
So
doesn't רבי מאיר... now we don't really have רבי מאיר explicit in
the משנה, Mishnah but he was in the previous משנה, Mishnah so
we assume if he's not speaking, at least he's tacitly agreeing to
this. He's the only named תנא, and we know that רבי מאיר
generally does not hold of that. So again we're going to speak
about why this is an exception to the rule of איסור חל
על איסור. issur chal al issur. מיהא דחל איסור לית ליה, Miha
dechal issur leis lei, he doesn't hold of it in normal cases,
but איסור מוסיף ואיסור כולל. issur mosif ve'issur kolel. He holds of
it when the new איסור issur includes more people or more, you
know, a greater audience or greater... So, to go, שבא על אמו
והוליד בת, Sheba Al Imo ve-Holid Bat, here's the scenario. He had
a daughter through his mother, so this girl is his daughter and
his sister. Now, that prohibition comes at the same time, דחייב אבתו
ואחותו בהדי הדדי אתי, de-chayav abito ve-achoto bahadi hadadi ati, that when
this girl is born, she becomes forbidden to him both as his
daughter and as a sister. The principle of איסור חל על איסור
issur chal al issur. is only when they're sequential. When they take
place at the same time, they both take effect. So those two
we got. ניסת לאחיו, Niset le-achiv, now she marries his brother. מיגו
דאיתוסף איסור לגבי אחיו, Migo de-itosaf issur legabei achiv, now she's forbidden
not just to him, there's a bigger audience that she's forbidden to
now. She's forbidden to all the brothers, right? 'Cause she's
the brother's wife of all of his brothers. So איתוסף itosaf to
a bigger audience, which is an איסור מוסיף. Issur Mosif. איתוסף איסורא
לגבי דידיה, Itosaf issura legabei didei, he also now becomes forbidden as
well. ניסת לאחי אביו, Niset le-achi aviv, marries his uncle. So now
she's forbidden also to a bigger audience, all of his uncles, all
of his uncle's brothers. מיגו דאיתוסף איסורא לגבי שאר אחי אביו, Migo
de-itosaf issura legabei shear achi aviv, since it's forbidden to all of
the uncle's
brothers, איתוסף לגבי דידיה, itosaf legabei didei, it's also forbidden to him
as well.
Okay, where were we? So in each of those stages, it started
at the same time, then each time she got married, he wasn't
the only one that became forbidden. A wider audience of people became
forbidden, so we say איסור כולל. issur kolel, הות לה אשת איש,
Havata leh eshet ish, now she's married, so now she's forbidden to
the whole world. מיגו דאיתוסף איסור לגבי עלמא, Migo de-itosaf issur legabei
alma, she's אסור Assur to everybody who's not her husband, so it's
a bigger audience. איתוסף נמי לגבי דידיה, Itosaf nami legabei didei, it
also adds a prohibition to him. הות לה נדה, Havata leh niddah,
now she became a נדה, niddah, so now she's אסור Assur to
one more person she wasn't אסור assur to before, her husband. מיגו
דאיתוסף איסור לגבי בעלה, Migo de-itosaf issur legabei baalah, now that she's
אסור assur to her husband, איתוסף נמי לגבי דידיה. itosaf nami legabei
didei. So he also gets, it's prohibited. So that's a way that's
not just doing a question of numbers, but explaining to you how
it's not a problem of איסור חל על
איסור. issur chal al issur. Yet another case. We have two more
משניות about these, about these cases of sex which has multiple prohibitions.
הבא על בת בתו, Ha-ba al bat bito, a man has sex
with his granddaughter. חייב עליה משום, Chayav aleha mishum, so we can
get multiple prohibitions. Question if the, whether in the משנה Mishnah it's
going to be six or seven. There's a case in parentheses. Let's
take a look. משום בת בתו, Mishum bat bito, his granddaughter, וכלתו.
ve-chalato. Now she could also be his daughter-in-law. How she could be
his daughter-in-law? Because now his son can't marry, because if it's his
granddaughter, it's his son's niece, right? If it's not, you know, daughter's
daughter, his son, it's his son's niece. You sort of see that,
right? If it's his granddaughter, he has a boy and a girl,
this, this man. His daughter has a girl, so that's his granddaughter,
but it's his son's niece. Is that, is that clear? Okay. So
this, so now his son married her. So now she's אסור assur
to him because of a granddaughter and because of a daughter-in-law.
By the way, the prohibition of daughter-in-law, the תורה Torah doesn't, never
says don't have sex with your daughter-in-law. It says אשה ובתה, ishah
u-vitah, the, a mother and her daughter. Okay,
so, actually
no, it does say daughter-in-law, sorry. אשה ובתה Ishah u-vitah is different.
וחמותו, Ve-chamoto, it does
say, I'm sorry, it does say, I'm sorry, I'm getting confused. Alright,
forget that. It does say daughter. Okay, whatever, fine. Sorry.
Okay, yes, so it's his daughter-in-law. Now, ואשת אחיו. ve-eshet achiv. Now
it's also his brother's, now, not also. It could also then, let's
say his son divorced her, and then this his granddaughter goes ahead
and marries his brother. His granddaughter can marry his brother, that's his,
that's the man's grand-niece. Okay, so his brother marries his granddaughter, now
she's אסור assur to him as his brother's wife. Okay, now, ואשת
אחי אביו, ve-eshet achi aviv, then they get divorced. All these prohibitions
remain even after death or divorce. Then they get divorced, then his
uncle marries her. It's his uncle's grand-grand-niece,
okay, so his uncle, his uncle's allowed to marry her, okay, but
then it's now forbidden to him not only as his daughter-in-law, granddaughter,
daughter-in-law, brother's wife, but now uncle's wife as well.
And each of those weren't previous prohibitions?
What do you mean? איסור issur. חל על איסור?
issur No, once she marries first his son, yes, then she marries
the son's brother,
son's
brother, son's uncle, yes. That's not a problem for an uncle to
marry his niece who happened to be his nephew's wife? No. Okay.
Now, I hear your question, but no, it would not, those things
would not be barriers for the next stage. Now, ואחות אשתו, ve-achot
ishto, there's a question whether to include that. It's a little bit
more complicated, but you can also get that it's his wife's sister.
How can his granddaughter be his wife's sister? Okay, because he married
a, I will try to do this with books here to do
generations, okay. So,
let's take a look. He, here's his wife, he married his wife.
Okay, his wife, I don't know, it doesn't matter. His wife, okay,
this is his wife's mother, okay, right? Yes? Okay, this is wife's
mother. His wife's mother happens to be his, wait, can this work?
His wife's mother can be that be his
daughter?
No, let's say easier. This is his wife's father. Okay? This is
his wife's father. His wife's father now went ahead and married his
grandmother, you with me? His wife's father married his grandmother and produced
a girl. Okay? I'm getting confused. His wife's father, hold on.
Let me check רש"י again. Okay, this made sense when I learned
it. One minute. אחות אשתו, Achot ishto, one minute. שהיה נושא את
בת חתנו. Shehaya nosei et bat chasno.
He was married
to... alright, let's give it a minute. שהיה נושא את בת חתנו.
Shehaya nosei et bat chasno. I know, this is where I needed
to bring the thing. One minute. את בת חתנו. Et bat chasno.
He was married to his father-in-law's
daughter, שהיא אחות בת בתו מן האב, Shehi achot bat bito min
ha'av, שהייתה לו בת מאשה אחרת. Shehayta lo bat me'isha acheret. ונשא
זה האב חמיו של בעל בתו. Venasa zeh ha'av chamiv shel ba'al
bito. Okay, he
had a daughter. Then,
okay, he had a daughter. One minute. Who's the Artscroll? Has like
a little chart.
Shh, you're distracting me. Shh. Okay.
Here. No, that's not the
picture. That's not the picture. Alright.
I had this worked out when I prepared it, I gotta tell
you, but I should have brought a chart with me. Oh my
god.
Okay. You know what? Let's keep on going. Let's... I can't... I'll
go back if I have time. Let's just... somehow it can also
be his wife's sister. That's the hardest case. So we'll put that
in parentheses for now. Okay. ואשת אבי, Ve'eshet avi, now she's a
married woman also, ונדה, Veniddah, fine. We have the aunt, she's a
ונדה. Veniddah. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yosei omer, and this is also
married, the same woman. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yosei omer, אם עבר
זקן ונשא חייב. Im avar zaken venasa chayav. Now,
this is the grandfather, he's אסור assur to his granddaughter in all
these ways. Now, if the granddaughter transgressed and married her, חייב עליה
משום אשת אב, Chayav aleha mishum eshet av, meaning his father. So
this man is אסור assur to his granddaughter in all these ways.
If his father, this girl's great-grandfather, transgressed and married her, then she's
also forbidden to her because of my father's wife. Okay, now of
course how could the grandfather have married her? It's his great-granddaughter, right?
That's forbidden. So we'll take a look in the גמרא.
Okay, סבא, Saba, maybe not בבא, Baba, maybe...
וכן הבא על בת אשתו ובת בתו.
Vechen
haba al bat ishto vebat bito.
So
everything we said before about daughter and granddaughter would also apply if
it wasn't daughter and granddaughter but it was stepdaughter and step-granddaughter. Okay,
because a man is prohibited on his daughter and granddaughter, he's also
prohibited on אשה ובתה ואשה ובת בתה. Isha uvita ve'isha uvat bita.
So everything... the first משנה Mishnah spoke about daughter and daughter had
six. So take out the word daughter, put in stepdaughter and you'll
also get six. The second משנה Mishnah we just did talked about
granddaughter. Take out the word granddaughter and put in step-granddaughter, wife's granddaughter,
and you'll also get the same number. Okay, we're not going to
figure that part out. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Okay,
דתני חייב עליה משום אשת אב. De-tani chayav aleha mishum eshet av.
So
it says that if... we're going to ignore the whole first part
of the משנה Mishnah. and hone in on the last line. That
if the man's father married her, this girl, his great-granddaughter, then you
also get the prohibition of father's wife. Okay, so the גמרא says
מישריא ליה? Misharya lei? Now, how can this man marry his great-granddaughter?
Now, since he can't, why does it matter? We're all talking about
prohibitions. Yes, but you will not have a prohibition based on marriage
unless the marriage is binding. And a marriage won't be binding if
it's an איסור עריות. Issur arayot. So if this man's father married
this girl, his great-granddaughter, it's not a binding marriage. So she can't
become אסור assur to him as, right, father's wife. So how's that
going to work? אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, so said אמר
רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, כגון שנפלו לו ליבום. Kegon shenafelu lo
leyibum. No,
what happened was was that this woman... that this girl became... that
there was a מצוה Mitzvah of יבום Yibum on her, which means
what? Remember, one of the scenarios was that it married his... his
father's brother... it became his father's brother's wife. So it was his
father's brother's wife. You with me? Then the father's brother died. Okay,
so then there's no kids. So now the father
has... So that's what the גמרא's going to say, but it's going
to say that's only רבנן. Rabbanan. Okay, we thought he could marry
her because it was his brother's wife. Now we're saying, no, it's
actually the brother died without kids, it's a מצוה Mitzvah of יבום.
Yibbum. So כגון דנסיב ליה הכי מאי עבר? Kegon d'nasiv lei hachi
mai avar? So what did he do wrong? He married his brother's
wife, the father. So אמר יעקב Amar Yaakov שעבר משום כלת בנו,
she'avar mishum kallat b'no, because it is his son's, it is his
son's,
what do you call it? His son's daughter-in-law. Okay? His son's
daughter-in-law.
Right. Why doesn't it just say it's his granddaughter?
A minute. It's his son's, so it's משום כלת בנו. mishum kallat
b'no. It's his son's daughter-in-law, it's his son's, like one of the
cases in the משנה Mishnah. was she, this granddaughter also became his
daughter-in-law. So now it is his son's daughter-in-law. So the גמרא says
שניה, shniyah, that's only a rabbinic prohibition. כדתני, Kidtani, like we taught
in a ברייתא, Braita, כלתו ערוה, kallato ervah, his daughter-in-law is prohibited,
כלת בנו שניה, kallat b'no shniyah, his son's daughter-in-law is only a
secondary ערוה, ervah, only רבנן. Rabbanan. וכן אתה מוצא בבת בנו ובת
בת בנו, V'chen atah motzei b'vat b'no u'vat bat b'no, ah, there
it gets to it. His granddaughter ובת בן בנו עד סוף כל
הדורות, u'vat ben b'no ad sof kol hadorot, that any granddaughter and
any later things is all רבנן. Rabbanan. Okay, so this case was
the great-granddaughter. So this case was the following. Okay, here it was
that it was the son's, the son's granddaughter. Okay, the son's granddaughter,
the father here, it's his great-granddaughter. But now we're saying great-granddaughter is
only רבנן. Rabbanan. Now this granddaughter also married the son's, this granddaughter
also married, also married, became his son's wife, so that was his
daughter-in-law. But this is the, but for his, the father here, it's
his granddaughter-in-law. That's also רבנן. Rabbanan. So that's רבנן Rabbanan and that's
רבנן. Rabbanan. And therefore the marriage when he marries her, it's able
to be binding. Ah, but wait, how could he marry her? She
was married to his brother, and that's a prohibition. No, the brother
died without children. So the brother died without children, there's a מצוה
Mitzvah of יבום, Yibbum, he's able to marry her. So why does
the משנה Mishnah, say עבר? avar? So no, he maybe, well that's
a question about whether שניה לעריות shniyah l'arayot in יבמות, Yevamot, but
whether, but no, that's why the משנה Mishnah, says עבר, avar, he
transgressed. But it was still binding. He shouldn't have done it because
it was still his great-granddaughter and his son's daughter-in-law, but those are
all רבנן. Rabbanan. So he transgressed those rabbinic prohibitions, he did יבום,
Yibbum, and now she's also אסור assur to the son as father's
wife. Okay? So that is the פשט pshat in that last line
of the משנה. Mishnah. Okay. What?
Okay, so now that we've done that, we've introduced רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi into the משנה. So now we've had all the fun before
with רבי מאיר, now we're going to ask it about רבי יוסי.
Rabbi Yossi. ומי אית ליה לרבי יוסי איסור חל על איסור? U'mi
it lei l'Rabbi Yossi issur chal al issur? Now that we've got
רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yossi name in the משנה, does רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi really hold of איסור חל על איסור? והתנן, V'hatnan, we taught
in the משנה, עבר עבירה שיש בה שתי מיתות נידון בחמורה. Avar
aveirah sheyesh bah shtei mitot nidon b'chamurah. If somebody did a sin
that has two prohibitions,
two things that you're חייב the death penalty, so you give him
the more stringent, right? Like סקילה, שריפה, הרג, חנק. skilah, sreifah, hereg,
chenek. So let's say you'd give him סקילה skilah over חנק chenek
or שריפה sreifah over חנק chenek because you did two prohibitions, you
get the, there's a gradation of the death penalties. רבי יוסי אומר
נידון בזיקה ראשונה שבאה לו. Rabbi Yossi omer nidon b'zikah rishonah sheba'ah
lo. No, you give him the first death penalty that was defined
vis-a-vis this thing. You know, this is the idea of אין איסור
חל על איסור. ein issur chal al issur. So what would be
an example? ותניא כיצד אמר רבי יוסי נידון בזיקה ראשונה? V'tanya keitzad
amar Rabbi Yossi nidon b'zikah rishonah? How does he, what does he
mean to say you don't give him the more stringent one but
the first one? Because he says the second one never took effect.
חמותו, Chamoto, let's say it's his mother-in-law,
ונעשית אשת איש. v'na'asit eshet ish. When he marries his wife, okay,
his wife's mother was single, divorced, widowed, whatever. Okay, so she was
only אסור assur to him as mother-in-law. Then she got remarried. Now
she's also אסור as married woman. Now normally you would say that
that's an איסור כולל, issur kolel right? Because it affects, or איסור
מוסיף. issur mosif. Now it affects more people. But רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi is not impressed, and this is why it's interesting. Because רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi normally says I'm not impressed with איסור כולל issur
kolel, and איסור מוסיף. issur mosif. I don't care that it affects
more people. This woman is only forbidden to him as mother-in-law and
does not become forbidden as married woman. The second prohibition doesn't take
effect even if it's a bigger prohibition. Okay. נידון משום אשת איש.
Nidon mishum eshet ish. So the רבנן Rabbanan say no, she's also
a married woman, and a married woman has a, and that's the
punishment you give him because that's a more severe
punishment. ואמר רבי אבהו מודה רבי V'amar Rabbi Abbahu modeh Rabbi I'm
sorry.
נידון משום חמותו. Nidon mishum chamoto. I'm sorry, excuse me, excuse me.
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says, I'm sorry, חמותו chamoto anyway is the
more severe prohibition because אשת איש eshet ish is
one minute. Right. שריפה. Sreifah.
Right, אשת איש Eishis Ish for married woman it's חנק Chanak and
for חמותו Chamoso it's שריפה, Sreifa, for mother-in-law it's שריפה. Sreifa. So
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says נידון משום חמותו. Nido Mishum Chamoso. It's
his mother-in-law, mother-in-law came first, that's the one that remains. Fine, anyway,
that's the more severe one. But let's say it was the reverse.
אשת איש שנעשית חמותו. Eishis Ish she-nasas Chamoso. That would be a
classic case. A married woman who then became his mother-in-law. That's a
classic case. A man marries a woman, the mother is, the mother-in-law
is married, she starts by being forbidden to him as a married
woman, then he marries her daughter, and then she's also forbidden as
mother-in-law. Now mother-in-law is the more severe prohibition, it gets שריפה. Sreifa.
Okay, so רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yose omer, so נידון משום אשת
איש. Nido Mishum Eishis Ish. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says
she's not forbidden as mother-in-law, she's only forbidden as married woman. Okay,
so here's רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yose's idea that you don't say איסור
חל על איסור even if it's a bigger prohibition. So you get
the case? So it starts with being his mother-in-law, and it starts
with being a married woman, then it also becomes his mother-in-law. רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose says the second prohibition doesn't take effect, you only
give the punishment of אשת איש Eishis Ish of married woman which
is the less severe, I mean they're both death, but it's the
less severe death. Okay, so now רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose doesn't hold
of איסור חל על איסור. So אמר רבי אבהו, Amar Rabbi Abbahu,
מודה רבי יוסי באיסור מוסיף. modeh Rabbi Yose be-issur mosif. He actually
does agree when the new איסור is bigger, adds more, adds more
people. וכן כי אתא רבין אמר רבי יוחנן מודה רבי יוסי באיסור
מוסיף. Ve-chein ki-asa Ravin amar Rabbi Yochanan, modeh Rabbi Yose be-issur mosif.
So he does agree when it adds more people. Now, how does
that work? How does that work then in the mother-in-law case? Why
do you always go by the first one if he agrees that
if the second one is bigger that it does take effect? Because
listen to it, because here's how it works.
If it starts
by being a married woman and then becomes his mother-in-law, the second
prohibition has no larger scope. This woman was אסור to the entire
world and now it's also his mother-in-law. So what? It's no larger
scope. So therefore it's no larger scope, it didn't take effect. So
therefore you go only by the first which is married woman which
is the lighter death penalty. What is the case he says you
don't, that you don't give the harsher death penalty when it starts
with, that you don't give the second one, meaning when it starts
with mother-in-law and then it goes ahead and also becomes a married
woman? So there the normal approach would say that that's a איסור
כולל, it's broader, and it should, איסור מוסיף, issur mosif, it should
take effect. So here the גמרא is saying it sure takes effect,
but who cares? The next prohibition of married woman is not more
severe, right? So it's not going to lead to a greater death
penalty. I don't think I explained that well, let me try one
more time quickly. Okay, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says you always do
the first prohibition. Okay, we assume that means that he categorically rejects
איסור חל על איסור. And the גמרא says no, he does not
categorically reject איסור חל על איסור. He actually says that when it's
broader it does take effect. But the way it'll work out will
be that it'll always be the first one. Why? Because if the
first one was mother-in-law and then came the broader one, married woman,
okay, yes, the married woman does take effect, but you know what?
You're still going to give him the more severe, the more severe
is mother-in-law, that was the first one. If it was the reverse,
first married woman and then mother-in-law, since mother-in-law is not broader, it
does take effect, and therefore you give him the first which is
married woman.
So yes, you give him the more severe.
No, you always give him the first. Right. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
says you always give him the first, not because he says a
second one can't take effect. A second one could take effect, but
in these scenarios where it takes effect, it'll always be the weaker
one. And therefore, and therefore he's safe to say you always give
the first. Okay, so רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose does agree by איסור
מוסיף. issur mosif. מאי איסור מוסיף דקא חפיל, Mai issur mosif de-ka-ha-fal,
let's just finish to the משנה. What's the example of איסור מוסיף?
issur mosif? דאיכא ברא לסבא. De-ika bra le-saba. So now you
have that when this guy's father married this woman, okay, let's assume
the son, the guy who was the focus of doing the prohibition,
also had a son. Okay, this man had, the man who had
his granddaughter and married his father, right? That guy also had a
son. When the father married her, she became אסור now to a
new person. She became אסור to his brother,
to, I mean this guy, I'm sorry, this guy had a son,
when his father married her, right, she now
became this son now became his daughter-in-law, well no, his grandfather's wife,
the grandson's became his grandfather's wife. Okay, so מיגו דאיתוסף איסורא לגבי
בריה איתוסף איסורא לגבי דידיה. Migu de-isosef issura legabei brei, isosef issura
legabei didei. So, oh
no, no, no, I'm sorry. I really knew I'd needed to write
this out. Excuse me.
This guy, it's his granddaughter, married his father. This guy, the grandfather
here, the father here, had a son. This guy has a brother.
Okay, so when his father marries this woman, this granddaughter, she becomes
אסור to his brother also as father's wife. Okay, so since she
also becomes אסור to this guy as father's wife, she can also
become אסור to him as father's wife. I think you have to
know
that the איסור of אשת אב eshet av is not only on
the father's wife, but also on the father's father's wife, and the
father's father's father's wife, and so on. It's a very broad איסור.
So, if this guy's father marries his granddaughter, she becomes his אשת
אב. eshet av. And since she's his אשת אב, eshet av, she's
also the אשת אב eshet av of his brother. And therefore, she's
אסורה asurah to both of them. Now, the question is, does the
איסור of אחות אב achot av also apply? Because she's also his
father's sister. No, she's his sister's daughter. Wait, let's look at the
chart again. This guy, his granddaughter married his father. So she is
his father's wife. She is also his granddaughter. Is a granddaughter אסורה?
asurah? Yes, she's a ערווה. ervah. But is she an אחות אב?
achot av? No. She's his granddaughter. So the two איסורים issurim we're
talking about are אשת אב eshet av and... what's the other one?
Let's look at the גמרא. The גמרא says, משכחת לה בבת בנו.
mashkachat lah be-vat bno. You find it by the daughter of his
son. Okay, so the daughter of his son is his granddaughter. If
his father marries his granddaughter, she is his אשת אב. eshet av.
And she is also his בת בנו, bat bno, his granddaughter. So
he has two איסורים issurim on her. One is אשת אב, eshet
av, and one is בת בנו. bat bno. Now, what about his
brother? His brother, she is also his אשת אב, eshet av, because
she's his father's wife. But is she his בת בנו? bat bno?
No, she's his brother's daughter. A brother's daughter is also an ערווה.
ervah. It's called a בת אח. bat ach. So for the brother,
she is an אשת אב eshet av and a בת אח. bat
ach. So both of them have two איסורים on this woman. That's
the case of the גמרא.